Matthew T. Bowen

Profile

Hello! I'm Matt, a student at the Royal Military College of Canada, where I am pursuing a Master's of Science degree in Physics & Space Science with a research focus on remote sensing. I graduated from Queen's University in 2018 with a Bachelor's of Science (Honours) in Physics and Computing Science. In addition to my studies, I have a background in electrical engineering through various jobs and volunteer positions. Currently, I am the Chief Technical Officer for the Queen's Space Engineering Team's Satellite Project, as well as a Junior Web Developer at Docupet Inc., a Kingston based technology startup.

Education

Royal Military College of Canada

Kingston, ON

Master's of Science - Physics and Space Science

2018 - 2020

- NSERC CREATE International Space Mission Training

Queen's University
Bachelor of Science Honours - Physics Major, Computing Minor

Kingston, ON 2013 - 2018

- Dean's Honour List recipient: 2013-2016

Experience

Queen's Space Engineering Team - Satellite Project

Kingston, ON

Chief Technical Officer

September 2019 - Present

- Manages and supports a team of 50+ students which designs and constructs a 3U cube satellite.
- Hired project managers for the major satellite subsystems.

Docupet Inc

Kingston, ON

Junior Web Developer

October 2018 - Present

- Responsible for large data set analysis and ETL using Python and MySQL.
- Developing Docupet Import Module using Django.

Royal Military College of Canada - Physics & Space Science Department

Kingston, ON

Observatory/Teaching Assistant

September 2018 - Present

- Trained students on reflector telescope usage for undergraduate astronomy courses.
- Guided student astronomical observing sessions.

Alma Mater Society of Queen's University Inc

Kingston, ON

Director of Information Technology

March 2017 - May 2018

- Member of the AMS Board of Directors, responsible for corporation-wide strategic planning.
- Maintained the technological infrastructure, performed account management, and oversaw project development.
- Trained and managed first level IT support staff.

Queen's Space Engineering Team - Satellite Project

Kingston, ON

Electrical Systems Design Lead

May 2017 - May 2019

- Designed and implemented the power generation and delivery system for CoSMOSat.
- Managed the periphery electrical subsystems, including command/data-handling, and attitude determination.

Queen's Solar Design Team

Kingston, ON

Electrical Projects Director

May 2016 - April 2017

- Delegated and monitored projects in data collection, energy storage, and low power home electricity usage.
- Designed and installed a fully off-grid photovoltaic power generation system for a 600sqft home.

Queen's Solar Design Team

Kingston, ON

Data Systems Manager

September 2015 - April 2016

- Designed and installed weather and data monitoring systems for the Queen's Solar Education Centre.
- Includes hardware implementation throughout the home as well as software development.

Arts & Science Undergraduate Society

Kingston, ON

Peer Tutor

September 2015 - Present

- Provides academic assistance for fellow students, as well as foster beneficial habits and skills in the tutee.

Queen's Athletics and Recreation

Intramural Official - Basketball

September 2014 - March 2018

- Ensured the safety and inclusiveness of participants, and upheld the regulations of intramural activities.

The Home Depot Kingston

Kingston, ON

Kingston, ON

Customer Service Associate

May 2018 - August 2018

- Provided consistent and accurate administrative and analytical support to the staff and customers of Home Depot.

School District #71 of British Columbia

Courtenay, BC

Groundskeeper and Delivery Driver

May 2015 - September 2015

 Maintained the infrastructure of schools, and engaged in new projects to enhance the teaching and recreational spaces at those schools. Compiled, loaded, and delivered equipment orders for school events.

Domo Japan Restaurant

Courtenay, BC

May 2014 - September 2014

 Processed customer orders quickly and efficiently in keeping with the high standards of food presentation, quality, and timeliness that are upheld at Domo Japan.

Skills Profile

Line Cook

Technologies Skills

Web: Django, Bootstrap, Symfony. General proficiency Astrodynamics and Orbital Mechanics

in JS/HTML/CSS/PHP/MySQL

Programming: Most proficient scripting in Python, Space mission design

experience in C, MATLAB, Java

Software: Space simulation in AGI STK Volunteer and team management

Graphic design in Inkscape/GIMP/Visio

PCB design in KiCAD/Eagle Agile development

3D design in SOLIDWORKS

Mathematica, LaTEX Scientific computing and ETL processes

Version control: Git

Projects

Polar Dust Loading Analysis using MetOp-A AVHRR Data

Royal Military College of Canada

Master's of Physics and Space Science Thesis Project

May 2019 - Present

- Studies the impact of dust aerosols on Arctic amplification models and the disappearing cryosphere.
- Utilizes Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer (AVHRR) imagery and novel distributed computing techniques to perform mass trend analysis.

NGVS Surface Brightness Profile Fitting

Queen's University

Honours Physics Thesis Project

September 2017 - May 2018

- Study the light profile of Virgo Cluster galaxies to detect the trace of stellar halos.
- Use of chi-squared and Markov Chain Monte Carlo minimization techniques to determine the light percentage contributed by halo stars.

Investigating Hydrodynamic Quantum Analogues

Queen's University

Physics Laboratory, PHYS 350

December 2016 - May 2017

By mechanically vibrating viscous fluids, several quantum mechanical effects can be demonstrated.

Implementation of Kalman Filters for Apogee Detection in Rocket Flight

Queen's University

Queen's Rocket Engineering Team

September 2016 - January 2017

- Research into the viability of using a Kalman filter to deploy airbrakes on atmospheric rocket flight.
- Implementation of algorithm using an Arduino platform with pressure altimeter and 9-axis accelerometer.

Determining the Width of the Kirkwood Gaps

Queen's University

Computational Methods in Physics, PHYS 313

September 2015 - December 2015

- Wrote a limited N-body code (in C) to simulate the motion of asteroids in resonance with Jupiter and Saturn.
- Co-wrote scientific report detailing the findings and results of the Verlet simulation.

Certifications and Courses

•	Amateur Radio Operator (callsign: VE3KSP) Innovation, Science, and Economic Development Canada	Toronto, ON <i>February 2017</i>
•	Graduate Professional Skills Certificate University of Saskatoon	Saskatoon, SK <i>August 2019</i>
•	Sexual Violence Bystander Intervention training Queen's University	Kingston, ON <i>May 2017</i>
•	Workplace Hazardous Materials Information System Queen's University	Kingston, ON <i>May 2016</i>
•	Working at Heights The Safety Guys	Kingston, ON June 2016
•	CPR-C First Aid Canadian Red Cross	Belleville, ON <i>April 2015</i>